Preliminary Inventory to the Wolfgang Wilhelm Sauer Papers, 1913-1989
Hoover Institution Archives
Wolfgang Wilhelm Sauer Papers,
1913-1989
90068
Sauer, Wolfgang Wilhelm, 1920-1989
68 manuscript boxes 27.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, correspondence, notes, curricular material, and printed matter, relating to the history and culture of Germany, German intellectual history, twentieth century German political history, the revolution of November 1918 in Germany, the relationship between President Friedrich Ebert and General Wilhelm Groener, the rise and nature of national socialism in Germany, and militarism as a factor in German history. Includes some papers of Wilhelm Sauer, uncle of W. W. Sauer, relating to jurisprudence and philosophy.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1990.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Germany--History.; Germany--Civilization.; Germany--Intellectual life.; Germany--History--Revolution, 1918.; Germany--Politics and government--20th century.; National socialism.; Nationalsozialistische deutsche Arbeiter-Partei.; Militarism--Germany.; Jurisprudence.; Philosophy.; Ebert, Friedrich, 1871-1925.; Groener, Wilhelm, 1867-1939.; Germany.; Sauer, Wilhelm, 1879-1962.
Biography
German-American historian.
Container List
- Part I
  - Personal files (Box 1.)
  - Flight tickets; information sheets on immigration, U.C. retirement system, Blue Cross
  - Letters and documents pertaining to his resignation from employment in the state of Hessen, his appointment at U.C. Berkeley, and his promotion
  - Reports on the state of research: 1976, 1980, 1981
    - Résumé and résumé notes (A 1)
  - "German History (1985)"
  - Manuscript pages for chapters 5, 6, 7, 8, 9
  - Notes and collected articles (A 2)
  - "Hist/Civ/Germ - Part I/Outlines/Romans and Germani"
  - Text outlines for Introduction (A 3)
  - "Hist/Civ/Germ - Materials II Antiquity - Germani"
  - Notes on materials read and notes for texts
  - Notes on statistics, chronology, archaeology, tribes
  - Xerox copies of articles (A 4)
  - "Prologue II: Christianization - Materials." Notes, including notes on German antiquity, christianization, chronology, Augustine, Bonifatius (A 5)
  - "Hist/Civ/Germ - Materials III (Medieval)"
  - Notes and Xerox copies of articles
  - Notes on methodology for medieval chapters, on monasticism, investiture conflict, Holy Roman Empire, and Minnesang (A 6)
  - "F. Prinz: Mönchtum"
  - Xerox copy (A 7)
  - "Dallas Clouatre - Feudalism"
  - Xerox copy (A 8)
  - "Hist/Civ/G - Class. Period 16th-18th Century Materials" (Box 2.)
  - Notes
  - Outlines and lectures texts for History courses
  - Notes on statistics, bibliography, Reformation, 17th Century, Thirty Years War (A 9)
  - "Germ. Hist. IV"
  - Notes, cut articles (A 10)
  - "History/Civ/G - Classical Period"
  - Notes and Xerox copies
  - Notes on intellectual conditions post-1648, bibliography for Frederick's attack on Silesia, dynastic revivals, 18th Century Romanticism, Reform Period and wars of Liberation (A 11)
  - "Germ. Hist. IV, 18th Century"
  - Notes, cut articles, Xerox copies
  - Text notes (A 12)
  - "Rokoko - Materialism"
  - Notes and cut articles, pictures and bibliography (A 13)
  - "Hist. Civ. G.-19th Century to 1914"
  - Notes, cut articles
  - Notes on 19th century, 1848, Bismarckian and Wilhelmine period (includes critique of Schlieffen Plan) (A 14)
  - "Germ. Hist. V - Materials"
  - Notes, cut articles, Xerox copy, text notes
  - Outline: Intellectual History, 1850-1890 (A 15)
  - "Grillparzer and Stifter"
  - Notes
  - Text notes on Stifter, Wagner (A 16)
  - "Materials VI (20th Century)"
  - Documents, notes
  - Text notes on Hitler and on Nazi inheritance
  - Notes on World War I, Versailles, Weimar, Nazi period, the post-1945 period (A 17)
  - "Germ. Hist. 20th Century" (Box 3.)
  - Notes and cut articles (A 18)
  - (No title)
  - Cut articles (incl. Bitburg) (A 19)
  - Manuscript: Chapter 5 with margin notes (apparently by another person) (A 20)
  - Manuscript: "Set III complete" (placed in manuscript box) (A 21)
  - Manuscript: "Set IV complete" (A 22)
  - Manuscript: " Set V incomplete" (A 23)
  - New folder - loose sheets on German history and Don Juan (A 24)
  - Contents of Manuscript (completed set: chapters 1-6)
    - Introduction
      - What is "German" History?
      - When does German History Begin?
      - Where is Germany?
      - No title
      - The natural Environment of German History
    - Chapter 1 - The Prehistoric Peoples of the North
      - Who were the Germani?
      - Tribal Cultures in Prehistoric Central Europe
        - Celts and Rhenish Germani
        - The East Elbians
      - Origins of Archaic Kingship
      - The Suebic Kingdom
    - Chapter 2 - Rome and its attempted Conquest of Germania 55 B.C. to A.D. 9
    - Chapter 3 - Roman Frontier Policy A.D. 14 - c. 160
    - Chapter 4 - The Tribal Kingdoms and the Great Invasions
      - The "Royal" Tribes
      - The Migrations
      - Raids and Invasions
      - Rome and the Invasions
      - The Proto-German Tribes
    - Prologue II - Christianization
    - Chapter 5 - Medieval Christianity
    - Chapter 6 - The Franks and the Irish Mission c. 500-700
      - The Conversion of the Franks and the Rise of the Frankish Kingdom, sixth and seventh centuries
      - The Celtic Church and the Irish Mission 7th century
  - "Summer Session - German Dept"
  - Notes, outlines, Xerox copies, administrative info. (B 1)
  - "German History (1985) Introduction"
  - Notes, drafts with revisions
  - Manuscripts on Introduction
  - Notes on Hillgruber plus 3-page manuscript "Die Bürde der deutschen Vergangenheit" (B 2)
  - "German History - Prologue I. Rome (1986)"
  - Outline: Plan for the German history project
  - Drafts on chapters 1 through 4, notes (B 3)
  - "German History - Part II. Medieval Empire" (Box 4.)
  - Notes, cut articles
  - Draft in Investiture conflict, chapter 10, Foundation of Medieval Empire (B 4)
  - "German History - Conclusion"
  - Short draft (B 5)
  - "Fragments 1985"
  - Drafts (B 6)
  - "German History: Who were the Germans?"
  - Outline
  - Original draft and second version (B 7)
  - "German History (1985) - Prologue Rome"
  - Drafts chapters 2, 3, 4 (B 8)
  - "German History. 1983 Version"
  - Manuscript chapters plus earlier fragments (B 9)
  - "German History. 1981-1982"
  - Early drafts (B 10)
  - "Frederick's Attack on Silesia"
  - Drafts, manuscript (3 versions, one in manuscript box) (B 11)
  - "Germany and Europe" (Box 5.)
  - Early drafts for German history, plus introduction (B 12)
  - "Fragments"
  - Drafts and manuscripts on classical humanism, classical anthropology and the Messiah (B 13)
  - "BRD/DDR (1945 ff)"
  - Cut articles, notes
  - Manuscript: "Die Studenten Rebellion von Berkeley und ihre internationale Bedeutung" plus drafts (manuscript box) (C 1)
  - (No title) (Box 6.)
  - Cut articles and notes (C 2)
  - "Nazism and Holocaust"
  - Cut article and notes (C 3)
  - (No title) (Box 7.)
  - Letters, airline tickets, brochures, concert programs
  - Prof. Sauer's letter against "self-evaluation" at U.C.B.
  - Bound xerox copies
    - "Unser vater und Wir"
    - "Unsere Clara und Wir"
  - Notes
  - Tenure Committee and Affirmative Action (C 4)
  - "Pluralismus" (Box 8.)
  - Letter, notes, History Department forms
  - Manuscript and text fragments for "Interessen-Gesellschaft"
  - Notes on "Soziologie der modernen Gesellschaft," "Definition von `Interesse`," "Marxismus Kritik," "Strukturbegriffe, insbes. `Klasse`"; etc. (C 6)
  - (No title) (Box 9.)
  - Manuscript - "The Birth of Classical Humanism" (Xerox) (D 1)
  - "Historical Statistics"
  - Notes (D 2)
  - "Hist. Civil. - Introduction, Concepts"
  - Notes on primitive society and civilization; cut articles. Clouatre paper
  - Manuscript: "Levi Strauss and the Savages" 2pp (D 3)
  - "Hist. Civil."
  - Bibliographical notes (D 4)
  - "Greco-Roman Antiquity"
  - Notes and cut articles (D 5)
  - "(Ancient) Christianity"
  - Notes (D 6)
  - "Judaism"
  - Notes (D 7)
  - "Juden and Christen"
  - Manuscript: "Juden und Christen" (Marked: not for publication; placed in manuscript box) (D 8)
  - "Civiliz. 1980 (8)"
  - Manuscripts: "Chapter 8: The Jewish Origins of Christianity"; "Chapter 9: Jesus"; old chapter 1 plus copies of classical humanism manuscripts (placed in manuscript box) (D 9)
  - "Birth of Class. Humanism"
  - Xerox copy of manuscript
  - Notes and drafts (D 10)
  - "Freedom and Slavery"
  - Manuscript: "Freedom and Slavery in Classical Humanism"
  - Different versions and drafts (one version placed in manuscript box) (D 11)
  - "Kap Hoorn"
  - Manuscript: "Über Heldentum"
  - Notes, drafts, bibliography and materials (placed in manuscript box) (D 12)
  - "Don Juan" (Box 10.)
  - Manuscript: "Über Don Juan"
  - Notes, drafts, and cut articles (placed in manuscript box) (D 13)
  - "Mozart II (opera seria)"
  - Manuscript: "Mozart, die Opera seria und die Krise der Kunst im 18.Jhdt." (marked private)
  - Notes, drafts, cut articles
  - Letter to Juliane (Xerox) (D 14)
  - "Mozart I (general)"
  - Manuscript: "Über Mozarts Kirchenmusik," 1986
  - Notes, drafts, cut articles (D 15)
  - "Mozart, opera seria" - Xerox
  - Copy of manuscript, 3rd version (D 16)
  - "Rousseau - sources"
  - Manuscript: "Rousseau or the Corruption of Truth"
  - Notes and drafts (D 17)
  - "Rousseau - Ms"
  - Manuscript: "Rousseau or the Authentic Untruth" (placed in manuscript box) (D 18)
  - "Rousseau - Version I"
  - Manuscript copy (D 19)
  - "China"
  - Notes and cut articles on India; Chinese chronology, poetry, philosophy and history (D 20)
  - "Book lists - Lectures 143 A-C" (Box 11.)
  - Reading lists and notes (E 1)
  - "Book lists - Seminars (103, 280, 285)"
  - Reading lists and notes (E 2)
  - "Examinations - Lecture courses"
  - Examinations and notes (E 3)
  - "Course Descriptions" (E 4)
  - "Exams. - M.A." (E 5)
  - "Free Speech"
  - Cut articles, pamphlets, materials (E 6)
  - "FU Krise" (Box 12.)
  - Manuscript: "Die Studenten Rebellion in Berkeley und ihre internationale Bedeutung" (placed in manuscript box)
  - Cut articles and handouts (E 7)
  - Course materials
    - History 100 (E 8 through E 13)
    - History 103 (E 14 - E 16, E 20)
    - History 104 (E 17, E 18, E 19)
    - History 143 (E 21 - E 34)
    - History 199 (E 35) (Box 13-14.)
    - History 280 (E 36 - E 41)
    - History 283 (E 42 - E 50) (Box 15.)
    - History 285 (E 51 - E 59)
    - History 299 (E 60)
  - Diverse course materials, grades and recommendations for graduate students (F 1 - F 27) (Box 15-18.)
  - "Misc. - Desiderata" (Box 18.)
  - Letters, request for recommendation, notes
  - Handwritten manuscripts: on Verdun, on "race and Intelligence"
  - Manuscript: "Die Reichsgründung im Spiegel von A. V. Werners Gemälde," plus drafts (L 1)
  - "UAM - PFA"
  - Pacific Film Archive programs (L 2)
  - (no title)
  - Xerox articles
  - Manuscript: "War as a Political Instrument - A Re-examination of Clausewitz's Theory," plus drafts (L 3)
  - "Englische Flottengeschichte"
  - Notes, Xerox articles (L 4)
  - "Naziism - Norton"
  - Notes (L 5)
  - "Biblio"
  - Bibliographical notes (L 6)
  - (no title)
  - Manuscript: "Facing the Destroyed Past: The Transformation of German Historical Consciousness since 1945," plus drafts and copies (Conference paper, 1977)
  - Notes: Otto Pflanze paper (L 7)
  - "Weimar Paper-2nd Version" (Box 19.)
  - Manuscript: "Weimar Culture: Experiments in Modernism," plus copies
  - Correspondence with Social Research (L 8)
  - "Weimar Conference - Paper"
  - Manuscript copies ("Weimar Culture"), conference paper ("Weimar Culture: Experiments on the Edge of Hope and Despair"), plus drafts (L 9)
  - "Weimar Conference - Drafts, Materials"
  - Reading lists for History 280, 285
  - Notes (L 10)
  - "Weimar Conference - Organization"
  - Correspondence; travel expenses; conference info.
  - Martin Jay paper (L 11)
  - "Gay, Weimar Culture"
  - Manuscript: "Die Geistesgeschichte der Weimarer Republik als Forschungsproblem," plus other drafts (Early drafts for above conference paper)
  - Notes (L 12)
  - "National Literatures"
  - State of research report, 1972
  - Various project descriptions: letters from Ernst Haas; info. packets; notes
  - Working titles for project: "The Nations and their Golden Ages"; "Literature, Language and Nation-Building in Europe" (L 13)
  - "Norton and Co. - (Nazi Revolution)"
  - Notes; correspondence
  - Agreement for tentative book: "The Nazi Revolution"
  - Outline for "The Nazi Revolution" (L 14)
  - "Peterson, Limits of Hitler's Power"
  - Correspondence (L 15)
- Part II
  - "Clausewitz" (Box 20.)
  - Manuscript: "War as a Political Instrument - A Historical Analysis" (previous version)
  - Old manuscript: "Clausewitz und der totale Krieg"
  - Drafts, notes, student papers (L 16)
  - "Cosmopolitanism"
  - State of research report, 1967-1968
  - History 285 course description and reading list; class papers, notes (L 17)
  - "Cosmopolitanism"
  - Project description, notes, student paper
  - Handwritten text notes: "Was bedeutet heute deutsche Geschichte?"; "Der kleindeutsche Nationalstaat"; "Tradition und Revolution im deutschen Nationalismus" (L 18)
  - (no title)
  - Manuscripts: "Über die Krise der deutschen Geschichte im industriellen Zeitalter"; "Über die gegenwärtige Krise der deutschen Geschichte"; "Nationalgeschichte und Universalgeschichte in der Industriegesellschaft"
  - Notes (L 19)
  - "Wiedervereinigung"
  - Manuscripts: "Nationalbewu(tsein und Wiedervereinigung"; "Alternativen zur Wiedervereinigung"
  - Notes, cut articles (placed in manuscript box) (L 20)
  - "Register für Exzerpte"
  - Notes and register for notes taken from readings (L 21)
  - "Exzerpte A-B etc. through "T-Z" (Box 20-21.)
  - Notes on readings (L 22 - L 29)
  - "Ungedruckte Quellen: Groener Nachla(" (Box 21.)
  - Groener Nachla(: notes and excerpts (L 30)
  - "Exzerpte ohne Verfasser"
  - Notes (L 31)
  - "Ungedruckte Quellen: Schleicher, Rat der Volksbeauftragten" etc.
  - Transcripts, copies of protocols (L 32)
  - "Militarismus - Kiepenheuer" (Box 22.)
  - Correspondence (requests for reprint permission) plus correspondence with Kiepenheuer (publisher)
  - Xerox copies and translation drafts (L 33)
  - (no title)
  - Xerox articles (L 34)
  - "Militarismus: Einleitung und Inhaltsverzeichni("
  - Table of Contents for "Militarismus" - list of English and German articles
  - Unfinished manuscript: "Einleitung"
  - Drafts, notes, reading list for History 103 (L 35)
  - (No title)
  - Manuscript: Militarismus in der Bundesrepublik?"
  - Xerox articles (L 36)
  - (Inaccurate title)
  - Xerox articles on militarism (L 37)
  - Xeroxes of journal articles, student papers, student recommendations (student recommendation returned to Department of History/UCB) (Q 1) (Box 22-25.)
  - "Darmstädter Arbeiten und Entwürfe (u.a. Führungsprobleme) ohne Endfassung" (Box 25.)
  - Outlines and notes (R 1)
  - "Nat'-Soz.: 1. Discussion IPW-Berlin 2. Vorträge - ASTA Berlin"
  - Typed outline: "Das Problem der Totalitarismus-Forschung"; plus handwritten outlines and notes (R 2)
  - .".. (illegible)... SS 1960"
  - Manuscripts: "Englisches und deutsches Heerwesen"; "Die politische Stellung der Armee in England und Detschland" (both incomplete)
  - Outlines and notes (R 3)
  - "Quellen, ungedruckte III (Nov. Revol.)"
  - Notes and transcripts from archives (R 4)
  - "Das Bündniß Ebert-Groener-Korrekturexemplar"
  - Manuscripts
    - "Werbetext zu: Militär-und Zivilgewalt in der Revolution: Das Bündniß Groener-Ebert 1918" (project description)
    - "Das Bündniß Ebert-Groener: Eine Studie über Notwendigkeit und Grenzen der militärischen Macht" (inaugural dissertation 1956)
  - Notes (R 5)
  - "November Revolution. Bündniß Ebert-Groener. Einleitung"
  - Manuscript: "Einleitung" (60 pp.; see separate "Manuscripts" description) plus drafts
  - Notes (R 6)
  - "November Revolution - Bündniß Ebert-Groener. I. Teil. 1.-6.Kap."
  - Manuscript chapters 1 through 6 (see separate description) (R 7)
  - "November Revolution. II. Teil. 7.-11.Kap."
  - Manuscript chapters 7 through 11 (see separate description) (R 8)
  - "November Revolution. III. Teil."
  - Manuscript chapters 12 through 15 (see separate description) (R 9)
  - (no title)
  - Unbound manuscripts, four additional chapters (see separate description) (R 10)
  - "Ungedruckte Manuscripte" (list inaccurate)
  - Manuscripts:
    - "Militärpolitik in der Weimarer Republik"
    - "German History in the First World War" plus drafts (R 11)
  - "Groener -Ebert"
  - Old texts, notes and Xerox copies (R 12 - R 14)
  - "Ernst-Reuter Gesellschaft" (Box 26.)
  - Notes (R 15)
  - .".. (illegible)... Interview"
  - Text outlines:
    - "Bericht über die Unterredung mit General Foertsch. München 28. and 31.1.1953"
    - "Bericht über die Unterredung mit Staatsarchivrat Böhm. München 26.1.1953"
  - Handwritten: "Unterredung mit Dr. Emil Franzel. 21.1.1953"
  - Notes
  - Copy of München Institut für Zeitgeschichte: "Der Chef des Ausbildungswesens" (R 16)
  - (inaccurate title)
  - Manuscript: "Die politische Geschichte der deutschen Armee und das Problem des Militarismus" plus copies (R 17)
  - (no title)
  - Notes (R 18)
  - "Reichswehr Bayerisches Hauptstaatsarchiv"
  - Typed archival notes (R 19)
  - "Seeckt Nachlaß"
  - Handwritten notes (R 20)
  - "Freikorps 1919/1920 - Materialsammlung"
  - Notes (R 21)
  - (no title)
  - Official publications (from U.S. Dept. of State; Bundeswirtschafts-Minist.(FRG); etc.) (R 22)
  - (new folder) (Box 27.)
  - History Dept. matters
  - Official publications, including "Report on the Prosecution of Nazi Crimes" (1965) and debate on the extension of time limit for prosecution of Nazi crimes (R 23)
  - "History of Prussia after 1945 - AHA 1970"
  - Manuscript: "Prussia in German Historiography after 1945 - Comment"
  - Drafts, copies, AHA program, Xerox articles (S 1)
  - "Jews in Germany"
  - Manuscript: "The Economic and Cultural Role of the Jews in the Weimar Republic" (comment on D. Niewyk paper)
  - Notes, drafts, Xerox copies (S 2)
  - "Nat'l. Soc. Bibliogr. Essay - AHA 1965"
  - Manuscript: "Fascism or Totalitarianism? Reflections on Recent Studies of Nazism"
  - Drafts, correspondence, Xerox paper (S 3)
  - "Nat'l. Soc. AHR Correspondence"
  - Correspondence and notes for publication of Nat'l. Soc. Journal article (S 4)
  - "AHA paper" (Box 28.)
  - Manuscripts:
    - "Nat'l. Soc.: Totalitarianism or Fascism"
    - "Historical Problems of the Nazi Era"
  - Correspondence, notes, Xerox copies: Jewish Center information (S 5)
  - "November Revolution. Teil II"
  - Chapter 15; drafts and notes (S 6)
  - "November Revolution. Einleitung"
  - Introduction: drafts and notes (S 7)
  - (no title)
  - Drafts and notes on letter to History Department concerning "Introductory courses" (S 8)
  - (no title)
  - Student paper (S 9)
  - "November Revolution - Ms. Nachträge, Ergänzungen, Allgemeines"
  - Drafts and notes (S 10)
  - "November Revolution - Einleitung"
  - Drafts
  - Handwritten outline for project
  - (note: plan calls for 10 parts and 32 chapters; titles of both do not match actual manuscript in file R) (S 11)
  - "November Revolution. Teil.I"
  - Drafts (S 12)
  - "November Revolution. Teil II"
  - Carbon copies (S 13)
  - "November Revolution Tel III" (Box 29.)
  - Drafts (S 14)
  - "November Revolution Teil. IV"
  - Carbon copies of Part IV, plus Xerox copies (S 15)
  - "November Revolution Chapter 16"
  - Draft copy: "Soziologische Probleme der Nov. Rev." (S 16)
  - "November Revolution - Exkurse"
  - Typed manuscripts on Dolchstoß-Legende, Kriegsziele, Schloßplünderrung, Volksmarineführer, Westheer 1918 (see manuscript description) (S 17)
  - "November Revolution - Misc. Ms."
  - Drafts (S 18)
  - "November Revolution - Ms."
  - Draft copies of first 14 chapters (S 19)
  - "November Revolution - Ms."
  - Draft copies (S 20)
  - "November Revolution - Ms. Anmerkungen"
  - Footnotes and Footnote drafts (S 21)
  - (no title)
  - Old draft chapters for November Revolution with different titles (S 22)
  - "November Revolution. Materials"
  - Notes, reading notes (S 23)
  - "Colloquium Dept. of History 1964" (Box 30.)
  - Notes, texts and outlines (S 24)
  - "Fitz, Rich"
  - Student paper (S 25)
  - "Soziale Revol. In Amerika (FAZ Aug. 1965)"
  - Manuscript (with missing first page)
  - Handwritten draft on Student Movement
  - Sauer letter to FAZ on student rebellion
  - Xerox letter by History Department to Die Welt
  - Xerox copies, articles, notes (S 26)
  - "Zentrum"
  - Manuscript: "Heiliges römisches Reich und deutscher Nationalstaat" (working title)
  - Draft copy and notes (S 27)
  - "Miscellaneous"
  - Tenure committee, notes, correspondence, History Department announcements (tenure files returned to Department of History/UCB) (T 1)
  - "Unfinished Business"
  - Drafts: "Formen des modernen Nationalismus"; "Zur Kriegsschuldfrage 1914"
  - History 124 course outline; History 143 reading list; History 280 info. and reading list
  - History Department announcements
  - Notes, newsletter, requests for references and recommendations
  - Transcript from Gen. Friedrich von Rabenau papers (T 2)
  - "AHA"
  - Manuscript: review of M. Göhring's book for AHR
  - Letter on Gagliardo manuscript
  - Correspondence with AHA, brochures, announcements (T 3)
  - "AAUP" (American Association of University Professors)
  - Information, newsletters, membership card (T 4)
  - "Supported Organizations" (Box 31.)
  - Information (on charities, non-profit organizations) (T 5)
  - "American Academy of Political and Social Sciences"
  - Invitation (T 6)
  - "Bund Demokratischer Wissenschaftler"
  - Information, brochures, correspondence (T 7)
  - "Central European History (Conference Group and Journal)"
  - Announcements (T 8)
  - "Conference Group on German Politics"
  - Correspondence, information, Xerox copies of conference papers (T 9)
  - "Department of History"
  - Departmental information (faculty office hours; etc.) (T 10)
  - "Deutsche Vereinigung für Politische Wissenschaftler"
  - Information (T 11)
  - "Ernst Reuter Gesellschaft"
  - Information (T 12)
  - "International Platform Association"
  - Information (T 13)
  - "Historische Zeitschrift / Historiker Verband" (Box 32.)
  - Information (T 14)
  - "Institut für Politische Wissenschaft"
  - Information, correspondence (T 15)
  - "Institute for International Studies"
  - Information, correspondence (T 16)
  - "IPSA" (International Political Science Association)
  - Information, correspondence (T 17)
  - "Legal History 1966/1967"
  - Notes and G. Caspar reprint (T 18)
  - "Membership Lists - Prof. Organizations"
  - Information (T 19)
  - "Leserzuschriften"
  - "Letters to Editor" by Dr. Sauer (T 20)
  - "Zeitschrift"
  - Manuscript: "Über die Gründung einer neuen westdeutschen Zeitschrift für Geschichtswissenschaften" (Nov. 1967)
  - Correspondence and notes pertaining to this concept (T 21)